all right welcome thanks everyone for
joining this is
the final recorded session on the first
half of
cover four it's August 22nd 2023
and
we are going to discuss chapter five so
before we look at what we might have
ahead of us from questions or anything
else
does anyone want to make any general
comments on five
I'm just anyone can can give a
give a thought
just since we're on chapter 5 in the
neurobiology
we talked I think a little bit in the
chapter 10 closing discussion for cohort
three about some of the topics like
what is empirical evidence or what is
any experimental setting have to do with
free energy principle octave inference
and and we reflect a little bit on this
recent paper
that like with isomura at all
that like
broke through kind of another level
not necessarily even from a epistemic
perspective oh I guess in terms of
people's awareness it was epistemic in
that sense
then I was thinking about
this was in 2018.
I mean it's the same title
I know that the work has proceeded a lot
since then so that's not the same they
rehash the same
but
in some ways because there is a
difference between map and territory
between like
models of X and X
in a way there's like this eternal
Gap
that just continues to swallow up
experimental results
um much to the Chagrin of people who
think that just one more experiment is
gonna
gonna Bridge or map the Gap
and that's kind of like what some of us
are told as graduate students a lot of
graduate school has to do with like
creating a data set and people get into
the zone of thinking that that one data
set is going to be
addressing the question even a narrow
one
and of course like if it's not helpful
then let's not waste our resources to do
that
but at the same time people were
um
saying that the relationship between
gene expression and behavior was
resolved in the 90s
and it's the same language that comes
out today and then even in this kind of
fractal free energy way
it's like what were we looking for in
the petri dish again
Ollie
yeah that was exactly uh what I was uh
gonna say because uh in fact I would
love to see in newer editions of the
textbook to uh to see some of the new
directions and what some people call
radical biology uh to be incorporated
much more uh that than we see uh
currently in the textbook because uh
actually the The Works of scientists
such as Michael 11 and even before that
I mean Varela Montana and copra
they show some
radically new approaches to see
see biology and and even life itself
through I mean the conceptions of
autopilotoisis and allopoiesis and other
uh related terms but I believe that
closer incorporation of these Concepts
uh into the textbook can help to see the
bigger picture which connects Bayesian
mechanics as an overarching theory of
every
quote-unquote thing to active inference
because
the way it stands now uh and in
particular the way chapter 5 stands now
there seems uh quite a big gap between
uh what Bayesian mechanics represents as
a theory of every thing and it's
neurobiological representation or I
don't know neurobiological evidence or
whatever but
if there was a
I mean more material on these new
directions of radical biology I believe
these gaps can begin to be filled and
the bigger picture can be
um can finally emerge as a kind of
continuous picture with without any
significant
um and possibly confusing gaps in
between
anyone else want to give a thought on
that
just one speculation here
the map territory Theory practice the
sort of dualistic dialectic is well
known
questions like what does math have to do
with Biology and what is
statistics have to do with something
like a system of Interest so
um that's kind of the classic
um
we're dealing with another
theoretical distinction within the
domain of theory
were making a distinction
not not
um
a uh homogenization but a distinction
between the more theoretical physics
axiomatic View
and the lens or tradition or method or
approach or process Theory described by
active inference
that level
of um disentanglement
of kind of like the platonic core
from the more manifest models in theory
but theory in practice
and that's like exactly where active
sits so I think in the live chat for the
Symposium session duvid and I were kind
of going back and forth
and his contention was like well octave
inference has been like really
um useful in the machine learning and
artificial intelligence space but it
hasn't it hasn't made any contributions
to to neuroscience
and then I mean there's so many angles
to take on that point but like one is um
is that it hasn't made many
contributions relative to what you
think another theory has done
or is it it hasn't made enough
contributions relative to what your
preferences for what it could have done
by this time are
that that's
um one angle but then the other angle
that kind of presented itself was like
like
are we looking for experimental
validation of the free energy principle
or are we looking for people who want to
apply active inference
and that's the experimental validation
I mean what if it was experimental
validation of sum of squares linear
regression on electronic Healthcare
record data
be like
talk about a non-sequiturer
decade after decade experimental
validation of linear regression on
rainfall and tree growth data
how many decades before you just say we
used a linear regression
and if you think we could have used it
better then tell us how or if you have
another model other than a regression
let's see it
but that mobilizes the discussion
in like
a very radical
way Ali
uh yes I I also don't think uh that
active inference or fep
uh can be considered as a kind of Niche
theoretical thinking anymore because uh
recently I I'm more and more often I
come across some articles or books that
don't mention active inference or fep at
all or I don't know any work related to
active inference but the ideas presented
in these works are very very similar to
what active inference to active
inferences assertions so
it it looks like there's
the box and active inference or fep fits
right into I mean it's a theory that is
proposed uh uh I mean at the right time
uh and uh for the Right audience I
believe because uh
if it were proposed it was proposed
about I don't know three decades ago uh
maybe uh or probably it could go to into
Oblivion without
um
uh people being aware of any of its
significance at all but uh as I say said
it seems like the present time uh is
kind of uh fertile for these kinds of
um
not radical but
a bit out of the box thinking that uh
would that can potentially help to
reshape our understanding of life
in its broader sense
so yeah again
its current status seems to me like it's
beginning to be
uh
mainstream or at least in the early
phases of
a mainstream theory is
truly evident from some recent work in
this area
yeah
and it's so fun to see the memes in the
narrative sharpen
like when I was just walking around a
few minutes ago I was thinking okay
reward maximization
or
Precision optimization on getting more
reward same thing but also surprise
bounding is more General than reward but
you could make a peer reward model
we see that in in the textbook
so it's like what's your first principle
reward
surprise bounding or something else
or nothing or you haven't thought about
it
it's all it's all fine
but which one of them is it
or you or do you want to pop out a level
and even have like a different way of
approaching the question
so it's not like presenting a closed box
it's like
a more dynamical frame
which is largely potentially even
overwhelmingly
congruent with simply modern statistical
physics
and again then do you want to say well I
have an alternate statistical physics
branch
or I have higher Visions for what
statistical physics could do than what
it is doing it's like congratulations
then you're a researcher now it still
may be decades or never until you make a
contribution
but that's exactly the
path of a researcher seeing an area and
then thinking that it can go beyond
and like well I don't have that
alternative proposal for Niche
construction yet but I want to be in the
game
to be there to recognize when it does
happen or I want to make something
happen eventually
but
merely waiting at the starting line
comparing Frameworks to
on
described alternatives
we barely even have the vocabulary to
describe some of these um
conversational patterns
and now we have more flexibility to like
pop out and pull back to the meta
science but again it's like okay so are
you saying we can't use math to use to
do in the context of Neuroscience
and some people may hold that
perspective and that may be the
conversation to have at that time
but once the um
or or somebody may think that the
engineering tools like Bert brought this
up many times in the symposium
that machine learning benefits greatly
from Decades of development on toolboxes
and uh
in in his section
he was like yeah this is like the
optimistic positive message is
within months to years and Carl also
alluded to it in the round table like
we will have
closer to push button
Solutions
so
I think that really contextualizes a lot
of what we're doing and learning when a
lot of these formalities are going to
get
just like simply baked in
and people will be engaging at at more
applied layers
but all in the context of chapter five
where a variety of empirical
data are being brought into play we're
talking about real Anatomy
talking about real reflexes
neurotransmitters real design patterns
in the nervous system in the body
so does anyone want to give a thought or
ask any chapter five related questions
all right let's just see if we can up
just see what comes through
okay
um schematic
in figure five one shows layer 5 of the
cortex projects to spinal pyramidal
neurons this can be interpreted as a
prediction
spinal motor neuron and spinal pyramidal
neurons are sometimes used
interchangeably
SP okay
anyone have a preference for which one
of these questions to jump into
um
I would be curious about the the
question regarding how do habits and
goals interact
um I found this chapter interesting in
part just because the introduction of
habits or like the e
variable I suppose
yeah well let's start with what is the
goal we're gonna have to reach outside
of the active inference ontology
to bring it in because we don't need
goals
although at the same time the term is
used
prolificately
let's see how it's used in five
this is a mixed mixed dialect
e and G are habitual and goal-directed
drives
that's a very interesting sense of goal
like in the um
football
soccer setting
the goal is like a fixed
external objective like a milestone but
a culminating milestone
but how is how is it being used here if
by goal we mean something that g
sharpens
well in that case well first let's look
at what e does e is the prior
on policies
so it reflects before the observation
comes in before updating has happened
what are the prior probabilities of
certain actions being taken
and then that observation may not
influence
e so e kind of gets passed through and
we see that in the basal ganglia second
example in the chapter
um or or it gets sharpened
so if we see expected free energy
minimization as being goal directed
certainly it's not sufficient to say
that goals are pragmatic only
because if we take everything that g
encompasses like that better policies as
evaluated by G are more goal directed
and inferior policies are less goal
directed then
up in the category of more goal aligned
like let's just say the two most goal
directed policies
they may radically differ in their
composition
because one may be heavily loaded on
pragmatic value
homeostasis bringing observations into
alignment with preferences and all that
and the other policy might have a good
expected free energy
because of its high epistemic value
and so it seems like at least just
locally here though probably elsewhere
in the book they're talking about goals
in just this kind of broader cybernetic
goal-oriented sense
here we see the goal is like the process
and the goal is this imperative
or maybe there's other ways to read it
too
but it's kind of like G is
it's like if you were trying to drive
somewhere
there's like a location you're trying to
get there with a location
and a Time
you could you could also think about
that as Precision in space and time
um
which decisions are going to be more
goal oriented well if the goal is just
the location on the soccer pitch
then the most goal-oriented policy is
the one that's like locally or globally
taking you closest to the location on
the soccer field
so that's a situation where like you're
like yeah there's time but really like
let's just pursue this the space or
location as fast as possible we'll get
there when we get there
um
but then if you say well we're going to
hold up both of these
features
in this driving example the the space
and the time but in G the epistemic and
pragmatic and we're going to say well
actually the joints
optimization of those two is what we're
going to call our goal
that's a little different sense of goal
but it is used here
and it's specifically used to talk about
how habits and goals differ
namely
where habits
are reflecting the prior probability on
taking different actions
kind of the pass-through model
where observations don't influence what
actions are likely to be taken those
still actions may be taken at in equal
frequencies whereas goal orientation
means an increasing role for expected
free energy in sharpening that policy
prior into policy posterior Ali
oh sorry uh well yeah another relevant
uh remark here is uh about this uh you
see uh there's this kind of
um teleophobia among biologists and uh
they usually try to uh avoid uh using
the word purpose instead of go because
they believe that although biological
agency implies a kind of a goal-directed
autonomy uh it doesn't necessarily
require for those agents to be
um to have any kind of purposiveness as
uh then it
would and
argue but
the problem here I mean the
distinguishing between these two
concepts uh is a kind of I mean as I
said it probably emerges from this
um teleophobia among biologists because
uh any talk of
purposiveness can be seen as a
provoking teleology which is something
that scientific culture
has been very averse from many centuries
ago but if we somehow Define goals or
purposes as a kind of mechanistic
lawfulness to
apparently purposive Behavior then this
dilemma between these two concepts would
probably be resolved because
in this case we have basically defined a
goal in terms of purposiveness so
they're not actually separate terms and
they co-constitute each other uh of
course the same kind of phobia
was evident probably much more
it was a bit more prominent
a couple of decades ago but it was also
evident in the for for the concept of
function but but it seems like this
phobia has been diminished in recent
years but nevertheless
this teleophobic
refusal to accept
purposes as real factors in biology
Still
Remains but
active inference and some of these
recent
progresses in biology as I said the
works of Michael Levin and others
are ways to somehow dismantle this
dichotomy and this uh teleophobia and as
David cracker would call to see complex
systems as a kind of teleonomic matter
so uh it doesn't necessarily something
that would require us to think about any
uh I don't know
Supernatural or Supernatural entities or
transcendental entities to get into the
picture we can talk about purely
naturalistic and mechanistic teleology
as well using these goals and purposes
in this kind of interrelated terms
yeah great comments one more piece on
that from like the so-called argument by
Design which is actually played a very
interesting role
arising most famously in the the
watchmaker analogy which is like you're
walking on putting aside the big meta
which is like what is the utility of any
thought experiment or any like little
narrative walkway that somebody provides
you it just is like if you look at a
watch
you're going to
infer intention of a Creator and so then
the argument sometimes plays out like
we'll look at all the small bones in the
ear or look at the way that the retina
is
um then the design argument became
actually one of the design and
Engineering became some of the key
pieces of the modern evolutionary
synthesis in evolutionary biology but as
Ali alludes to there always was this
kind of teleophobia as Mike Levin calls
it sometimes or just like this
awkwardness around like well are we
going to appeal to just all functions
just as they are so that's like a sort
of like functional teleology just or or
does one go the kind of tehar De
chardine
Omega Point Bobby azarian angle like
that is the account and where the
radical biology in a way speaks that or
cuts the knot is like
the the hidden fallacy in the watchmaker
um
thus
is like
it tries to transfer the analogy of a
top-down function
[Music]
bestowments
whereas if we have
self-creating or co-creating or embedded
arisel
then we can say
yeah like the Circadian circuit
arose through Evolution and development
as a bottom up
self-created
in relation
mechanism for just that telling time
so at the level of linguistic course
training it makes sense to say that the
circadian clock keeps time just speaking
super broadly here
like a watch keeps time
but there's a critical difference which
is that the watch was like an
engineering artifact as the top-down
projection of a cognitive system
whereas some kind of like internal
organic representational system like a
circadian clock
is actually like a bottom-up
construction so like there just isn't an
issue
with describing or understanding
goals
and it's just an English word anyway
once we really start to get into the
specifics with agency and habit
a lot of this
may just dissipate
and in the more recent multi-scale
formalizations
the habits
can include like like the phylogenetic
scale
or the Habit could refer to just what is
passed through moment to moment in the
organism's life
or you can imagine this as being like a
intergenerational transfer
and a habit or a a developmental
tendency for a habit is also able to be
inherited
Andrew any thoughts on that or
wherever anyone else wants to go
um
no I don't have any
any deeper thoughts on on that I suppose
uh I guess I'm more interested in the
sort of computational aspect of it
as far as message passing goes rather
than um I mean I find all of the the
kind of the more abstract philosophical
side of of discussing what goals are
very interesting and in certain ways
very important
um when putting together a framework but
I guess here it's just
um I just found it interesting like oh
now we have habits in addition to
G which I previously considered to be
like just expected free energy
um but maybe I have my terminology mixed
up here is this G not the same as um oh
you you're totally right and I think
that that's just it's a little
um coincidental alliteration
and G never stands for goals it's just a
total typographical spandrel
so then the question becomes what is the
goal concept broad enough to Encompass
what it is that g does
and that's clearly not the same thing as
just like
the mile marker on the side of the road
but then a little bit more on the um
computational side
e primes the pump for the procedure that
g does
like the shape of the variable e
is the same shape that gets taken into G
the cells in the in the variable e
are what get sharpened by G
as it iterates through every policy and
calculates its expected free energy
so e and G
um
they both are engaging with this policy
variable
which is just a list of all the possible
policies so all the affordances
basically raised to the power of how
many time steps that you want to play it
out for
and
um
G sharpens what e provides
or modifies what e provides
and the gamma the temperature
parameter on on decision making
here
associated with dopamine neuromodulation
is
modulating that trade-off
between the the E pass forward
in the indirect pathway
so it's kind of type one and then the
um
policy updating driven by G
sure no thanks for kind of giving more
explanation on that it's um
so I find that very interesting then
because at some point in here it refers
to like uh
um sorry I can't find it immediately but
the use of the word context
um so so
um it's as if e
so those are your priors over policies
and so you're lacking
something like context of the given the
agent is lacking context in a given
moment I suppose such that one might
like rely upon
um their habits to deal with the
scenario whereas G is in fact taking
into account not only e but context in
the sense of oh uh the agent is taking
in observations
um it's Computing expected free energy
um it
I I guess I'm just putting everything
together as far as I understand it so
it's e Prime you start with e
you enter into some context with a
variety of observations or otherwise
from there you begin to compute G and
then from there you can start to
actually score potential policies to be
taken with some of them deemed to be
more minimizing a free energy given the
context and so on
versus Eve which seems to be more or
less static through the whole
computation dissolve that track
yeah great points so definitely when you
set it up you could make it so that ee
is fixed or that you can make it so the
E counts like earns that's one simple
learning technique but but it's a great
connection with context so like let's
just say that we are um playing cards
and then it's like
the main idea is we have beliefs about
how we act in particular contexts you
know I we're playing um 21 Blackjack and
I stay 80 of the time just habitually
so the two cards are dealt face down
habit is before the context is
recognized or uh paying no attention to
context
you take the the 80 stay
and then context we could translate as
basically like the sensory observations
and and the ensuring sense making
so now you look at the cards
and then
you're going to sharpen
through G
again that doesn't even mean it's better
than playing on reflex it doesn't mean
it's better than playing 50 50 it
doesn't mean you're going to win it
doesn't mean like all these like kind of
outcome oriented
possibilities in the world
but
it is the case like if one lets the card
that they saw influence their decision
making
we would model that as
the generative model using expected free
energy based policy evaluation
planning as inference
even if it's just one time step planning
that's
how we understand the situation where a
person who stays eighty percent of the
time
looks at the cards and makes a decision
that differs from that
or it could be who else is at the table
and then so then they they want to make
a certain move not because it aligns
their pragmatic value with winning the
pot but that it gains them information
about who they're playing with and their
strategies
which speaks this kind of thinking
through other Minds
topic and also just the need to build
specific generative models
because how could we talk about what is
an expected free energy minimizing
decision in the context of a of a
blackjack game
unless you've delineated like what is
even being considered
but now think about how far people go
beyond the Blackjack game talking about
what does and doesn't reduce expected
free energy
so thanks again for that that was very
clarifying and uh yeah so suddenly the
phrase is um model free versus model
based systems in this context makes a
lot more sense
yeah model free just kind of flailing
but that may be in effect to the flail
and it may be an effective way to go or
model based is where you get more
explicit structuring
um okay this one's a freebie
popcorn in the chat or however what
other neural systems are interesting to
model
other than the three that are in chapter
five
what's another mammalian
neural region or non-mammalian
system that would be fun to model
actually I would very love to see active
inference applied for modeling emotion
circuitry and
in fact it's an ongoing going projects
of mine but it proves much more
complicated than I previously imagined
but
um
as uh well some preliminary Works have
been done
by people like Ryan Smith and others but
there still needs I mean lots of work
for these kind this kind of momming to
uh
to be as mature and sophisticated as
some other areas that active inferences
has been applied to but uh for me
personally uh it's um it's really
interesting Prospect to see
how modeling uh emotions are a dream and
even modeling
emotion itself
using active inference terminology and
Concepts would reveal
some deep mysteries about emotion and
its relation to cognition and other
mental faculties so yeah that's one area
of Interest
rule a few things that
um Dr NL Lemke said today in the round
table that that stakumi one was like
about this
co-presentation I won't even call it
attention or a paradox between accepting
higher power and taking agency in one's
own life but she related to her like
context in the Psychiatry and addiction
setting and then also it came up later
like
um with precision
and uh monitoring and the increasing
ability for
monitoring of our biometrics
and like just the bigger picture on how
like maybe knowing your heart rate at
all times
maybe it spirals off in all these
different ways like now you have too
much Precision on heart rate you're
paying too much attention to it or
um
there was just a lot of interesting
pieces there and then also there was a
discussion about like limitations of the
brain as a predictive system
or of modeling the brain as a protective
system
and it yet again another place where
action comes in
to like
save the day slash slam dunk because
it's like well yeah when it's a
prediction about what you're about to do
it's only a prediction for so long
and then it happens
so it's like a lot of these like
prediction like they're they're often
implicitly in this kind of like
um archaic dark room setting
like where actions can't be taken
and it's just a perceptual question
but we know that perception plays a
actually plays a role in perception
itself through the isocade and through
the example at the beginning of the
textbook where like you can't determine
the texture of a fabric without moving
your finger
so it's like well
it's not demeaning to say that it's
predictive
when it gets implemented a split second
later
but all but so much of the predictive
discussion focuses just on like on like
you know Predictive Analytics predictive
forecasting
what's going to be the most popular song
next year
and that's a very removed way of
considering the role of action and
inference
but yeah a lot of neural systems to
model
okay just kind of a related question
what point does oh Ollie go for it
uh yeah I just wanted to
um
make a maybe a sideway remarks but
there's even this recent Trend toward
um the the probabilistic aesthetic
theory of art so and especially as
applied to avant-garde or Contemporary
Art so and then they call it predictive
Arts uh so uh one Pioneer in this area
is
um Conrad uh woynovsky which is uh who
also has an upcoming uh book
um I think it will be published in
February 2024 but yeah as you said these
kinds of probabilistic modes of
um sensing and making sense of reality
uh has it started to being applied to
even Aesthetics and
I mean Contemporary Art criticism as
well
well yeah I remember this this paper
this was I was in the um the the buy it
based on the title phase of my graduate
school access to free printing and I
just remember thinking this was like the
funniest and boldest title
because there's like several sentences
and it has all these weird Illusions in
it but um
this uh and I think active
goes beyond it but on the left side here
is the time scales
like from like the the 100 millisecond
you know visual region this and that and
the shorter term memory and okay we're
at an exhibit so there's the context
window of like what we've seen from the
exhibition
and then it even expands out to like
let's see how slow it gets in the very
slowest
very very slow
like lifelong Mastery I think or
something
transformation
60 plus seconds but then but but then
the transformative capacity and and and
uh
Bert talked about in the Symposium with
like the need for longer term
lower
resolution estimates
and how a key engineering question right
now
is being able to adjust basically the
computational resources allocated to
different kinds of estimates
so I gave an example of like if you're
going to drive three quarters of the way
around a roundabout
you don't need to know like what
centimeter it's going to be at
you just want to know what Lane you're
going to be in
but the next centimeter might matter for
the next centimeter
and so being able to like dynamically
tune or develop hierarchical structures
or other kinds of inference uh
architectures
where
we're getting a lot of like bang for the
buck because
we're using our CPU cycles and other
resources But ultimately attention and
Trust on
like
we're not calculating 12 decibel points
for something that could have just been
left at one and vice versa
where does reasoning sit in five five
I think it depends what you Define
reasoning as
but looks like in some previous
discussions we've talked about like
reasoning as unconscious inference
and just depends on what is meant by
reasoning is it any kind of Reckoning
or is it specifically like a consciously
aware one but that's that's a good
question is fep applicable to any system
let's vote The Perennial question
coming to flip a coin I'm gonna flip a
coin it's gonna be a real coin flip I'm
gonna use the real entropy of my room
it was not a coin with heads or tails so
it was not a conclusive answer
but I hope that in future
figure out more
generalist tools to interact with
Bayesian mechanics
I think I remember this question being
asked and who asked it
and the mechanisms in the brain
at the uh
on this topic actually the uh the first
presentation
in the symposium
Andre bastos
this was very much like
welcome to the Neuroscience conference
like not not
grandstanding at all with a theoretical
connection just like this is how it's
being visually processed
here's how we're doing more and more
measurements here's how theories guiding
our experiments
and it did come up to this like um
multi-band Alpha Beta and then the gamma
like the differential which we talked
about I think in one or two times ago
differential frequencies
well
cohort three
um sorry Daniel there was this question
I think the one down the last one you
okay I talked about about uh
is there any alternative representation
for something like that yeah are there
alternative visualizations that better
uh so I think we have an additional
answer to this question now uh because
of chantal's work and string diagrams so
okay
yeah
yeah I I believe Jana made this
image
and then I know that Bert
brookers has done a ton of work in like
alternative Visual and and tactile
metaphors and then on the more formal
side you're absolutely right that the
string diagram may even or some of the
representations that Sanjeev is
developing in the fundamentals work
certainly we're seeing things that are
like familiar but also different
so
great works cohort for
um that's our final recorded discussion
next week we'll have um
feedback and talk a little bit then
we'll take a few weeks off
and uh
get the gang back together for cohort
for part two and for cohort five and
we'll um talk more next week about the
timing for everything and see what works
for people so
thank you all
till next time thanks everyone bye thank
you